Mss.Rec.49 Mss.Rec.49
American Philosophical Society
Recordings of Cherokee, Creek, Naskapi, Penobscot, Sioux, Santee, Tutelo, and Winnebago
1935-1937
Mss.Rec.49
American Philosophical Society
4.0 Reel(s)
Recordings of Cherokee, Naskapi, Penobscot, Sioux (Santee), and Winnebago materials. The copies in the APS Library were made from discs recorded by Speck in the field in various places in the United States, Canada, and Labrador between 1935 and 1937.
4 sound tape reels (1 hr., 45 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, full track, mono; 7 in.
Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
Related Archival Materials
The Frank G. Speck papers in the APS Library contain many of Speck's original field notes and texts of this collection, but they are not cross-referenced to the recordings. Researchers should consult the APS American Indian guides under specific tribes and languages contained in this recording for possible further documentation.
Location of Originals note
Some of the original discs are in the Archives of Traditional Music at Indiana University in Bloomington, Indiana, while others are in the Museum of Primitive Art in New York.
Cherokee language; Creek Indians--Music; Creek language; Dakota Indians--Music; Dakota language; Flute--Performance; Hunting songs; Hymns.; Lullabies; Micmac Indians--Music; Naskapi language; Penobscot dance; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot language; Prayers.; Santee dialect; Songs.; Sound recordings; Tutelo Indians--Music; Tutelo language; Winnebago Indians--Music; Winnebago language
- Audio recordings
  - Flute Solo, 1937; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:17; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Scope and Contents note
    Performed by Jasper Blowsnake, Thunder Clan. Some sound distortion at beginning of program due to degradation of digital tape copy.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Phonograph record) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Flute--Performance; Winnebago Indians--Music; Wisconsin
  - Flute Song: Paint Song, 1937; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:19; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    "No words for song but symbol is man puts on paint on face for good luck when he goes to make love, to play contest game, to visit in hope of getting a gift, to engage in war expedition." Performed by Jasper Blowsnake, Thunder Clan.
  - Flute Solo, 1937; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:39; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Performed by Jasper Blowsnake, Thunder Clan.
  - Words and Voice of Flute Solo, 1937; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:13; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Winnebago Indians--Music; Winnebago language; Wisconsin
  - Hunting Song, 1935; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Pitan, Pien; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Location identified as "Naskapi, Labrador, St. Augustine Band." Most likely Saint-Augustin, Basse-Côte-Nord Territory, Québec.
    Hunting songs; Naskapi Indians--Music; Naskapi language; Saint-Augustin (Québec)
  - Dance Song for wedding, 1935; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:42; Mistenapeo, Jerome; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Naskapi dance; Naskapi Indians--Music; Naskapi language; Saint-Augustin (Québec); Weddings--Songs and music
  - Lullaby No. 1, 1935; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Nelson, Roland; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    The singer, Roland Nelson, was also known as Chief Needahbeh. Possibly identical to other Penobscot "Lullaby" from same collection. See Related Recording.
    Lullabies, Penobscot; Maine; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot language
  - Lullaby No. 2, 1935; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:35; Nelson, Roland; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    The singer, Roland Nelson, was also known as Chief Needahbeh.
    Lullabies, Penobscot; Maine; Penobscot Indians--Music
  - AD O WA - Thanksgiving Song, 1936; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:10; Buck, John, Jr.; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Identified as Tutelo, but may be in Cayuga or Onondaga.
    Cayuga language; Grand River (Ont.); Onondaga language; Tutelo Indians--Music; Tutelo language
  - Thanksgiving Song, 1936; 01-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:16; Buck, John, Jr.; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Bird Calls, 1936-08-20; 01-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:20; Cruikshank, Allan D.; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Birdsongs--Maine; Medomak (Me.)
  - Snake Dance, 1936; 01-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:56; Nelson, Roland; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Maine; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot language
  - Lullaby, 1936; 01-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:09; Nelson, Roland; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Micmac Dance, 1935; 01-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:45; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Maine; Micmac Indians--Music; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot language
  - Wedding Dance Song, 1935; 01-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:57; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Maine; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot language; Weddings--Songs and music
  - Micmac Dance, 1935; 01-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:59; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Micmac Dance, 1935; 01-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:30; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Wedding Dance, 1935; 01-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:06; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Wedding Dance, 1935; 01-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:01; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Wedding Dances, 1935; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:26; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Maine; Penobscot dance; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot language; Weddings--Songs and music
  - Social Dances, 1935; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:02; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Maine; Penobscot dance; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot language
  - Pedlar's Dance, 1935; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:33; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Moose and Caribou calling, 1935; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:03; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Caribou hunting; Hunting songs; Maine; Moose hunting; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot language
  - Hymn - "You, Me, Jesus", in Latin, 1935; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:14; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Catholic Church--Hymns; Latin language; Maine; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot Indians--Religion
  - Hymn and Prayers, 1935; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:13; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Catholic Church--Hymns; Catholic Church--Prayers and devotions; Maine; Penobscot Indians--Music; Penobscot Indians--Religion; Penobscot language
  - Hymn and Prayers, 1935; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:03; Nicholas, Louis; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Penobscot Wedding, 1935; 02-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:46; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Thibodeau, Joe
  - Gambling song for Mocassin dance, 1935; 02-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:15; Sky Eagle; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Dakota Indians--Music; Dakota language; Gambling--Songs and music; Santee dialect; Santee Indians--Music
  - War Song, 1935; 02-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:54; Sky Eagle; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Dakota Indians--Music; Dakota language; Santee dialect; Santee Indians--Music
  - Mocassin Game song, 1935; 02-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:58; Sky Eagle; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Mocassin Game song, 1935; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:59; Sky Eagle; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Dakota Indians--Music; Dakota language
  - War Song, 1935; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:41; Sky Eagle; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Hunting and Sucat lodge conjuring songs, 1935; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:40; Mistenapeo, Jerome; Pitan, Pien; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Bear hunting song, 1935; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:32; Mistenapeo, Jerome; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Bear hunting; Hunting songs; Naskapi Indians--Music; Naskapi language; Saint-Augustin (Québec)
  - Otter hunting song, 1935; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:40; Mistenapeo, Jerome; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Hunting songs; Naskapi Indians--Music; Naskapi language; Otter hunting; Saint-Augustin (Québec)
  - Story of Long Life and Going to Heaven, 1936-01-05; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:44; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; West Long, Will
    For Speck's original field notes concerning this program, see Ms. Coll. 126, Box 11, IV(17D2). See Related Resource.
    Cherokee (N.C.); Cherokee Indians--Folklore; Cherokee language
  - Bear Hunt Song, 1936-01; 03-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:44; Driver, Wesley; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    For text of this program and Speck's original field notes see: Ms. Coll. 126, Box 11, IV(17D3). See Related Resource.
    Bear hunting; Cherokee Indians--Music; Cherokee language; Hunting songs; Ravensford (N.C.)
  - Counting, 1936; 03-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:44; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Swallow, Ben
    Cayuga language--Numerals; Grand River (Ont.); Onondaga language--Numerals; Tutelo language--Numerals
  - Stomp Dance, 1935; 03-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:31; Alexander, Matty; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    [Alabama?]; Creek dance; Creek Indians--Music; Creek language; Stomp dance
  - Two Hymns, 1935; 03-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:14; Alexander, Matty; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    [Alabama?]; Creek Indians--Music; Creek Indians--Religion; Creek language; Hymns
  - Otter song in medicine lodge when candidate is shot with shell, 03-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:002:29; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Singer and date of recording not given. Probably recorded between 1935-1937.
    Winnebago Indians--Music; Winnebago Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Winnebago language; Wisconsin
  - Peyote song; 1st song of meeting at sundown, 03-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:46; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Peyote songs; Winnebago Indians--Music; Winnebago Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Winnebago language; Wisconsin
  - Flute song, 1937-05-13; 03-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:25; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Flute love song: two chiefs, 1937-05-13; 03-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:50; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    "Girl's song. A girl, a daughter of the chief sings this song. She says 'I'm looking for a man (Chief's son) who wears a big stamped brooch on a cord around his neck.'" Performed by Jasper Blowsnake, Thunder Clan.
    Flute--Performance; Love songs; Winnebago Indians--Music; Wisconsin
  - Flute song for drinking, 1937-05-17; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:46; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Drinking songs; Flute--Performance; Winnebago Indians--Music; Wisconsin
  - Words & Voice for flute song for drinking, 1937-05-17; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:43; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Drinking songs; Winnebago Indians--Music; Winnebago language; Wisconsin
  - Flute Song - "I Want To See My Dear Uncle", 1937-05-09; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:07; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Words and Voice for Flute Song - "I Want To See My Dear Uncle", 1937-05-09; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:46; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
  - Flute Song for Sleeping Baby, 1937-05-17; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:20; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Flute--Performance; Lullabies, Winnebago; Winnebago Indians--Music; Wisconsin
  - Flute Song, 1937-05; 04-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:30; Blowsnake, Jasper; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950